A Guide to the Papers of the Virginia Quarterly Review, 2000-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Virginia Quarterly Review 2000-2003
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-24/3/1.051
3000 items, 10 Hollinger boxes, 4 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.)
Acquisitions
The collection was an archival transfer from the Virginia Quarterly Review to theSpecial Collections on April 20, 2005
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Quarterly Review was established in 1925 and was originally conceived by President Edwin Alderman in 1915. President Alderman wanted the University of Virginia to publish a national periodical that "was solidly based, thoughtfully and wisely managed and controlled ... a great serious publication wherein it shall be focused and set down the very best thought ... of men everywhere in the nation and the world on vital questions in the fields of Economics, Politics, Ethics, Literary Interpretation and Historical Analysis...."
The first editor was James Southall Wilson, followed by Stringfellow Barr, Lambert Davis (who was able to maintain the journal through the Depression) Lawrence Lee, Archibald Shepperson, and Charlotte Kohler. The VQR was in the hands of its first woman editor during World War II when the men were away at war. Kohler's tenure lasted for an impressive thirty three years. In 1975 Staige Blackford became the editor and continued the high standards set by President Alderman until his retirement and death in 2003. The next editor was Theodore "Ted" Genoways who with support from key staff has continued to uphold the Virginia Quarterly Review as "a national journal of literature and discussion." (Quotes are taken from Staige Blackford's foreword in the Anthology of the 75th anniversary publication, "We Write for Our Own Time")
Scope and Content
The collection consists of editorial correspondence with contributors during the tenure of Staige Davis Blackford, Jr. (1975-2003) and the beginning of Ted Genoways' tenure (2003). Included are almost all of the literary figures of this period, and many from other fields. Included are authors' original manuscripts, (volumes 76-79) and some book reviews, newspaper clippings and magazine articles. Of interest is correspondence from George Core, editor of the Sewanee Review, who wrote to Staige Blackford about the future director of the Virginia Quarterly Review. He mentioned his concerns about the potential difficulties of a new director managing a staff and being an editor. The collection is about 3,000 items, 10 hollinger boxes, and 4 linear feet.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and the correspondence is organized in alphabetical sequence by author's last name
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - 2000 Winter Volume 76, No. 1, 1/2 Issue (Box-folder 1:1)
  - 2000 Winter Volume 76, No. 1, 2/2 Issue (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 2000 Spring Volume 76, No. 2, 1/2 Issue (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 2000 Spring Volume 76, No. 2, 2/2 Issue (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 2000 Summer Volume 76, No. 3, 1/2 Issue (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 2000 Summer Volume 76, No. 3, 2/2 Issue (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 2000 Autumn Volume 76, No. 4, 1/2 Issue (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 2000 Autumn Volume 76, No. 4, 2/2 Issue (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 2001 Winter Volume 77, No. 1, 1 Issue (Box-folder 3:1)
  - 2001 Spring Volume 77, No. 2, 1 Issue (Box-folder 3:2)
  - 2001 Summer Volume 77, No. 3, 1 issue (Box-folder 3:3)
  - 2001 Summer Volume 77, No. 3, 1 issue (Box-folder 3:4)
  - 2002 Winter Volume 78, No. 1, 1 Issue (Box-folder 4:1)
  - 2002 Spring Volume 78, No. 2, 1 issue (Box-folder 4:2)
  - 2002 Summer Volume 78, No. 3, 1 issue (Box-folder 4:3)
  - 2002 Autumn Volume 78, No. 4, 1/2 issue (Box-folder 4:4)
  - 2002 Autumn Volume 78, No. 4, 2/2 issue (Box-folder 5:1)
  - 2003 Winter Volume 79, No. 1, 1 issue (Box-folder 5:2)
  - 2003 Spring Volume 79, No. 2, 1/2 issue (Box-folder 5:3)
  - 2003 Spring Volume 79, No. 2, 2/2 issue (Box-folder 5:4)
  - 2003 Summer Volume 79, No. 3, 1/2 issue (Box-folder 5:5)
  - 2003 Autumn Volume 79, No. 3, 2/2 issue (Box-folder 5:6)
  - 2003 Autumn Volume 79, No. 4, 1 issue (Box-folder 6:1)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - 2001 Editorial Correspondence, # items (Box-folder 6:2)
    Correspondence from the editor to authors letting them know whether their writing was accepted or rejected by the Virginia Quarterly Review
  - 2002 Editorial Correspondence, # items (Box-folder 6:3)
  - 2003 Editorial Correspondence, # items (Box-folder 6:4)
  - 2001-2003 Correspondence of Staige Blackford, # items (Box-folder 6:5)
  - 1977-1983 Correspondence of Staige Blackford and Greg Orr, # items (Box-folder 6:6)
    There is correspondence and poetry submissions
  - 2001-2003 Correspondence about poetry, # items (Box-folder 6:7)
    Correspondence and information about how the poetry would be organized in the journal
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-A, # items (Box-folder 6:8)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-Bacon-Bogaty, # items (Box-folder 7:1)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-Boland-Boyd, # items (Box-folder 7:2)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-Cadmus-Coppedge, # items (Box-folder 7:3)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-Core-Cushman, # items (Box-folder 7:4)
    Of interest is correspondence from George Core, editor of the Sewanee Review, who wrote to Staige Blackford about the future director of the Virginia Quarterly Review. He mentioned his concerns about the potential difficulties of a new director managing a staff and being an editor
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Daniels-Fessler, # items (Box-folder 7:5)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Finley-Furgurson, # items (Box-folder 8:1)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Gaines-Havird, # items (Box-folder 8:2)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Mays-Just, # items (Box-folder 8:3)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Kalserlian-Livingston, # items (Box-folder 8:4)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Lodato-Murray, # items (Box-folder 8:5)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Nace-Osborne, # items (Box-folder 9:1)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Paddock-Pushcart, # items (Box-folder 9:2)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-R, # items (Box-folder 9:3)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors-Sadler-Skloot, # items (Box-folder 9:4)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Slavitt-Tucker, # items (Box-folder 9:5)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Uchida-Whitfield, # items (Box-folder 9:6)
  - 2000-2003 Correspondence with Authors Williamson-Zwiep, # items (Box-folder 9:7)
  - 2001-2003 Correspondence with publishers (lists), # items (Box-folder 10:1)
    Poet 's Market Update Sheet, Long Ridge Writers Group Market Directory, information about listings, awards, workshops, and grants
  - 2002 Financial, # items (Box-folder 10:2)
    Capital One miles and correspondence about finances
  - 1994-2003 Newspaper clippings and Magazine articles, # items (Box-folder 10:3)
  - 2000 Recognitions, 1 item (Box-folder 10:4)
    There is a certificate of recognition for the Virginia Quarterly Review
  - n. d. Restricted, # items (Box-folder 10:5)
    There are items that have social security numbers
  - 19982000 VQR 75th Anniversary, # items (Box-folder 10:6)
    Included is Staige Blackford's foreword in the VQR Anthology, "We Write for Our Own Time." The Anthology was published in celebration of the 75th anniversary of the VQR and was a collection of the best articles compiled from the publication.